<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The booke of the holy societye commonly called of tvvelve conteyning the lytanies, and prayers, vvich are to be sayd by those vvho are of that Societye. To obtaine of God the grace to dye well. Lately translated out of the French language for the benefit of English Catholikes by N.N. a Catholic gentleman.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837765</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1035:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The booke of the holy societye commonly called of tvvelve conteyning the lytanies, and prayers, vvich are to be sayd by those vvho are of that Societye. To obtaine of God the grace to dye well. Lately translated out of the French language for the benefit of English Catholikes by N.N. a Catholic gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Byfield, Nicholas, 1579-1622, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Anderton, Lawrence, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>N. N., catholic gentleman.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>131, [12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Laurence Kellam,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Douay :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Nicholas Byfield.</note>
                  <note>N.N. = Lawrence Anderton?.</note>
                  <note>A translation of an unidentified French original.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church. --  Society of Twelve --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Confraternities --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BOOKE OF THE HOLY SOCIETYE COMMONLY CALLED OF TVVELVE <hi>Contayning the Lytanies, and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, vvhich are to be ſayd by thoſe vvho are of that Societye.</hi> To obtaine of God the grace to dye well. <hi>Lately translated out of the French language for the benefit of English Catholikes by</hi> N. N. a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke gentleman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Orate pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at Douay BY LAURENCE KELL<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>
               <p>Saluos nos fac Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Deus noſter,</p>
               <p>Et congrega nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationibus:</p>
               <p>Vt confite amur no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſancto tuo,</p>
               <p>Et gloriemur in lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de tua.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 105.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:2"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE DEVOVT READERS.</head>
            <p>AS it is moſt certain, that we ſhall all of vs die once; ſo is it no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe certain that after our death we shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a doome of an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuocable ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernall life, or aeternall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2106:3"/>death, accordingly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we shall be found wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy or vnworthy at tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hower: And therfor i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth vs very near<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo to prouide our ſelues whilſt time permitteth that at the laſt hower we may be found in ſuch caſe, as is moſt befitting for that end, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all ayme at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which is happye life withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end. This conſiderati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2106:3"/>hath from my very childhood taken ſuch deepe impreſſion in my hart, that although to ſatisfye my curioſitye, I haue trauailed ouer the greateſt part of Europe, yet in my trauailes I had alwayes this end ſett be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore myne eyes, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue wher euer I might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earne, what courſe was beſt to be vndertaken for à man to ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2106:4"/>(as far as the inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of this mutable world will permitt) of à good and happy end. I ſaw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning ther was no better ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye could be had in this world of dying well, then to liue well: And for this reaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that ſaying of S. Bernard. <hi>In Religione homo viuit purius</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In Religion a man liueth more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2106:4"/>purely, falleth more rarely, riſeth more ſpeedily, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth more warily, recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the dew of gods grace more frequently, repofeth more ſecurely, dyeth more confidently, is purged from his ſinnes more quickly, and rewarded with glory more aboundantly;</hi> For this reaſon, I ſay, I could haue bene well content to haue imbraced à reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious courſe of life; but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2106:5"/>I eyther found indeed the conſtitution of my body too weake, or at leaſt the cowardeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my mynde made me flatter my ſelfe with that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipt, which diuerted my thoughts from ſo high an entrepriſe. Att the length co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thorough France, by the prouidence of God, and the care of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2106:5"/>my good Angel, as I preſume, I mett with a friend who beſtowed on me one of theſe little bookes, ſett forth in the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch language; which, after I had well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſed, and pondered, gaue me ſuch content, and ioy by cauſe it ſuted ſo well with my wiſhes, and preſented me ſo plaine, and eaſye a way to what I principally
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2106:6"/>aymed att, that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured my ſelfe to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the holy Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation or Confrater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitye, which is herein diſcribed. Afterwards comming into England and there diſcouering my treaſure gotten in France, I was follici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome of my fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, whoſe requeſts were commaunds vnto me, to tranſlate the ſayd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2106:6"/>booke into owre lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. I did ſo: and it began by little and little to grow into that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall liking of ſo many, that it ſeemed too to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious to tranſſcribe ſo many copyes. For which reaſon I gaue my conſent it ſhould be printed, that ſo ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction might be giuen to all. And loe here the booke: which if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2106:7"/>to the ſpirituall benefitt of your ſowles, I beſeech you lett me haue ſome part of your prayers; and that is all the recompence I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of you, either for my labour, or good will.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your fellow partener in your afflictions for gods cauſe. N. N. a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke gentleman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:7"/>
            <head>The authors inſtruction to the Reader that is, or deſireth to be of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietye.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OE truth is more appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which doth both teach and aſſure vs that euery liuing ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt once dy, to liue agayne
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2106:8"/>ther in heauen with the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and bleſſed Soules, or in hell with the damned &amp; wretched ghoſts, ſince this is the laſt ſentence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which there is noe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale; neuer to be reuew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed agayne, pronounced by the mouth of god our ſouueraigne iudg. And truth it ſelf by the apoſtle in theſe termes; <hi>It is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt once dye and after that comes iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> For which cauſe the moſt important and ſerious
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2106:8"/>buiſines that a Chriſtian man can haue in this world is to learne to dye well: For this is the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Sciences. And thereto ought wee to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye that ſayeing in the ghoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell ſoe much pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by our ſauiour to S. Mary Magdalene. <hi>But one thing onely is neceſſary.</hi> Whereupon S. Iohn doth eſteeme, and call thoſe onely bleſſed amongſt mortall men who dye in our lord: that is to ſay in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2106:9"/>his grace; <hi>Bleſſed are the dead vvho, dye in our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe ſince it is ſoe that eyther from à good, or euill death, the eternall and chiefe felicity is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued, or els euerlaſting and dreadful miſery, if there be any thing, deare reader, which thou oughſt to haue in ſingular reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation whilſt thou doſt reſide in this valley of teares, it is to ſearch and knowe the meanes which thou muſt vſe and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2106:9"/>practiſe to render the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage out of this mortall life, as much as in thee lyeth, moſt eaſy and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured. And to this end I haue bene willing to laye downe for thee, at the end of theſe prayers, ſome wholeſome leſſons for thy inſtruction, howe thou oughſt to behaue thy ſelf both in ſicknes and in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alth, to the end thou maiſt more happily finish thy dayes and life. Of which leſſons the principall, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2106:10"/>moſt aſſured (next to à good life) is to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe as you shall heare hereafter in fitt place to the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and merits of the Saynts, and aboue all of the moſt holy, and euer glorious mother of god. In which I shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto thee (beloued reader) certayn deuout and religious perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well inſtructed, caſt themſelues one daye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſpired from god, vpon that conſideration
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2106:10"/>that our good mother the church doth call the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed virgin, mother of God; <hi>the Gate of heauen,</hi> and <hi>doore of paradiſe:</hi> &amp; that shee doth daily ſing vnto her; <hi>Marye mother of grace, mother of mercy, defend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our aduerſary and receiue vs at the houre of death.</hi> But this was performed with ſoe ſerious attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſoe much feruor of deuotion; that from that time they reſolued to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe themſelues alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2106:11"/>with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to her, and to implore her ayde and ſpeciall aſſiſtance that they might more duely diſpoſe themſelues for that difficult, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous paſſage of death.</p>
            <p>For theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they did agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to ſay euery daye the Lytanyes of our Ladye of Loretto to the honor &amp; glory of her name, one for another; as alſoe the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers of the moſt glorious Patriarchs S. Ioſeph, S.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2106:11"/>Auguſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, S. Barbara, to whom they particarly deuoted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that by they interceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght be aſsiſted in theſe theyr indeauours.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as noe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can fully poſſeſſe that high vetrue of Charity without hauing à parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular care of the wellfare and ſafty of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; to prouide alſo that theyr ſmall number in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to come might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in this deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to augment the effectuall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2106:12"/>merit of theyr prayers by à laudable and holy multiplication, they did aduiſe amongſt themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and determine, that each one of them should aſſociate to theyre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany twelue deuout per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that thoſe twelue if they would, when the occaſion should be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red might likewiſe each one of them aſſociate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther twelue, and they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe euery one of them twelue others, and ſoe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2106:12"/>from one to another all thoſe, whoe should from time to time be added by any one, that had bene formerly admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, should haue the ſame power, which thoſe had whoe did admitt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And hence it doth proceede, deuout reader, that this Company is very fitly named at this time the holy ſociety of twelue, Whereunto ſince that time ſoe many are vnited in France, Italy, Germany
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2106:13"/>Spayne; yea euen as farre as the Indyes, that they are accompted at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of eyther ſexe, men and woemen, more then three, or foure hundred thouſand of the ſocietye, But whereas almoſt infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite perſons men and woemen cannot (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to read) ſay the foreſayd litanies it hath bene thought by ſome of the principal moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and affectionate to the ſayd holy aſſociation,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2106:13"/>that in ſtead of them thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat are admitted, which cannot reade, ſay theire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eads; and for the pſalme <hi>De profundis,</hi> which thoſe whoe are more learned ought to ſay for ſuch ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es as are departed of the ſayd holy Company, shall ſay 3. <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> and 3. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe to the end that thoſe, who are admitted, may not erre in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, whoe they are to admitt into the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2106:14"/>ſayd holy aſſociation; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were good, as ſoon as they shall be receiue to regiſter and write th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> downe in ſome ſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> booke; or els, which we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> better, and wherein ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is more merit, euery on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them shall prouid twelue of theſe littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bookes to giue them gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis to each one of thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom they shall admitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo shal he know by the fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nishing and diſtribution of his bookes that the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2106:14"/>of thoſe whome he may admitt is compleat and ended.</p>
            <p>Another meanes more certaine and ſutable to the condition of ſecular perſons, eſpecially woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is, to intreat him that shall admitt them, if he be à prieſt, or religious man, to accept and take the charge vpon him to aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate for them ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as he shall iudg in poynts of religion to be moſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2106:15"/>giuing him the tw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elue bookes, which they haue prepared for that purpoſe; nor ought thoſe prieſts or religious men refuſe this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion, and act of charity; but rather ought to ſeeke and dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it. Yea they ought not to admitt but very few, or ſcarce any ſecular men at all, eſpecially woemen; without this condition, to witt that they shall not receiue any one without the knowledg of their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2106:15"/>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſor; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that great profit will redound from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the holy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which otherwiſe by degrees might be filled with à great number of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertins, and debaushed perſons without deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in the end would bring dishoner to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietye. By which meanes the ſayeing of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay should be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed; <hi>Thou haſt multiplyed the nation, but hast not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed theire ioye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer this holy and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2106:16"/>flourishing Company, with thoſe prayers which are exerciſed therein hath bene receiued, and allowed by many graue and renowned perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of the chiefe of the cleargy as of the ſeculars. By famous and learned preachers and by good, and holy religious men, whoe haue bene admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from diuers orders both auſtere and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. By whom all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2106:16"/>Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, perceiuing the fruit and proffit which muſt needs ariſe to the church of god from this laudable and holy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, doth labor to haue it approued, authoriſed, and inriched by the holy apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique ſeat with the treaſures of the ſayd church obtayning for it plenary indulgences in forme of à Iubilie, which thoſe of the company shall gayne twice in theire life, that is to ſay,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2106:17"/>then when they shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the ſayd holy So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and at the article of death, and other plenary indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces likewiſe, with the deliuery of à ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purgatory, to be applyed by manner of ſuffrage to ſuch ſoules, as are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſayed holy ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etye, which they may gayne as well vpon all the feaſts of our bleſſed Lady, as of the foreſayd bleſſed S. Ioſeph, S. Francis, S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin, and S. Barbara,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2106:17"/>with this condition, that thoſe whoe are of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety doe confeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to allowed Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and communicate vpon the ſayd feaſts.</p>
            <p>And that they may be made pertakers of ſoe many good prayers, which are continually offered vp by ſoe deuout ſoules, and in ſoe many parts of the Chriſtian world, it is requiſite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enter into this holy ſocietye to haue à<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2106:18"/>to liue &amp; die ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and withall to obſerue as they shall be able, all that which shall be heere. after ſett downe although there be noe obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or tye of conſcience, other then that which euery Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath to liue well, and ſerue god, and to loue theire neighbour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2106:18"/>
            <head>VVHAT IS TO BE DONNE BY THOSE VVHO DESIRE TO BE ADMITTED INTO THIS SOCIETYE?</head>
            <p>FIrſt of all he that will enter into the ſayd holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany muſt cauſe himſelf to be receiued and admitted by one whoe hath bene formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2106:19"/>whoe shall make his reception ſoe much more gratefull and meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious before god, as he himſelf shall be more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendable in deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, holynes of life, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; which poynt is ſoe important, and of that conſideration, that thoſe whoe demand to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ought to vſe all meanes poſſible, that it may be done by ſome reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, or ſecular church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoe hath the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2106:19"/>to be à man of good life, or by ſome ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whoe as much as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne frailty will admit, is irreprehenſible in his life and conuerſation.</p>
            <p>Secondly he muſt euery daye without faile ſay the letanyes, which are ſet downe in theire place: the Antheme; <hi>Sub tuum praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium:</hi> the prayers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſual deuotions that doe follow, &amp; the pſalme <hi>De profundis:</hi> and ſuch as ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not read, theyr beads
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2106:20"/>with 3. <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and 3. <hi>Aue Maria;</hi> as hath bene formerly mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Thirdly; He muſt ſay the ſayd letanyes with the prayers for all thoſe of the ſociety, as euery one of them doe ſay them for him; &amp; he muſt beare them in memory as much as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; cheefely him, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in all the reſt of his prayers and oraſons; if he be à prieſt, in all his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2106:20"/>maſſes; if à religious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or woeman, in all theyr meditations, diſciplines, faſtings, watchings, and ſuch like exerciſes of mortification; and that he loue them, honor, and aſsiſt them aſwell corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, as ſpiritually, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his power, and the neede that they shall haue.</p>
            <p>Fourthly; He muſt ſay the forſayd prayers to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of god, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsion and fauor of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2106:21"/>our bleſſed Lady, and of the forſayd Saynts, the grace to dye well, and that with as much deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and attention as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he can, indeuoring with all his power, by his good life, to make himſelf meritorious of that grace: For as ſaynct Auguſtin ſayth he can hardly dye ill, whoe hath liued well, &amp; he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcarcly dye well, whoe hath liued ill. And it is, as a ſecret iudgment of god, noted by the ſame
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2106:21"/>S. Auguſtin in his ſermon of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: <hi>It is iuſt o Lord that he whoe whilſt he liued was forget full of thee, at his death should forget himſelf:</hi> that is, his owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſacraments, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution &amp;c? <hi>and dye like à beast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude thoſe of the company are exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and intreated in our lord Ieſus Chriſt to beare in memory and carefully to practiſe theſe fiue poynts which followe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2106:22"/>
The firſt that aſſoone as they can they should free themſelues from mortall finnes, if eyther they doe belieue, or doubt that they are touched with any; flying by all meanes poſſible thoſe occaſions which they knowe doe cauſe ſoe great à miſerye; and that where they are able to hinder it, they doe not ſuffer that any offend god in theyr preſence, or in any other place where
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2106:22"/>they haue power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>The ſecond poynt that they both confeſle and communicate if they can, beſide thoſe dayes which are appoynted therefor, as wee haue shewed, euery month.</p>
            <p>The 3. that they heare euery day maſſe, if they canne doo it without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice to that whereunto they are obliged; and that they pray for the catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que church, and for our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2106:23"/>holy father the pope, for the king and ſtate, and for the kings aſſue; for the peace and vnity of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princes, for the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of hereſyes, for thoſe that are in mortall ſinne, for ſuch as are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted &amp; in temptation, for thoſe that are in the agonye of death, and for theyr enimyes.</p>
            <p>The 4. that they inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to diſcharg them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues faithfullye, and with conſcience of ſuch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2106:23"/>dutyes, and obligations as belong to theire charge, &amp; vocation whereto they are called.</p>
            <p>The 5. that euery night they make, as they are able, an examination of theyr conſcience, and ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay before or after it, the prayer which is vſed to obtayne a true contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for theire ſinnes, which doth beginne: <hi>My lord Ieſus;</hi> with the next following prayer to our bleſſed lady; which exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2106:24"/>may be reduced for ſuch as eyther knowe not how, or cannot im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye themſelues longer therein to two poynts. The one to giue god thanks for all the graces, &amp; benefits, which wee haue recieued at his hands, cheefly that he hath that day preſerued vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mortall ſinne, &amp; ſudden death, and infinite dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers aſwell ſpirituall as corporall, which haue that very day fallen vpon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2106:24"/>ſoe many others better, and more conformable to the diuine goodnes then wee. The other is to fift and ſearch out into what, and how many offences wee haue fallen, or pex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or cauſed others to fall; then to demand pardon for them, and to propoſe vnto our ſelues to confeſſe, and amend them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="blessings">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2106:25"/>
            <head>OF THE GREAT BLESSINGS WHICH THOSE VVHOE ARE OF THIS HOLY SOC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TYE DOE RECIEVE.</head>
            <p>IF thou be in ſinfull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of life, thoſe who are of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany through out the whole world by theire prayers and merits diſpoſe thee, to leaue ſuch ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of life, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg thy ſinne, and that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2106:25"/>thou mayſt not dye in it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If thou be in ſtate of grace, they pray to god to conſerue thee therein, &amp; to augment and confirme it vnto thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thou doſt participate of the infinite good workes of ſoe many good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as are admitted to this ſocietye.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They help thee by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ire prayers to obtayne the excellent guift of final perſeuerance, and other vertues, which are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2106:26"/>as charity, patience, chaſtitye, deuotion &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They ayde thee alſo to obtayne of god that he would vouchſafe to keep thee from ſuddayne, or at leaſt from vnprouided death: And from falling into mortall ſinne: and in caſe thou doe committ any, that he would ſoe powerfully in ſpire thee with his grace that thou mayſt preſently riſe from it againe. And alſoe that he would aſſiſt thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2106:26"/>thy enimyes at the hower of thy death.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſacred virgin mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, and the glorious patrons thereof, Saint Ioſeph; S. Francis; S. Auguſtin; and S. Barbara, whom thou haſt ſoe often called vpon for theſe ends, and ſoe many thouſands as are of this ſocietye which dayly pray for thee, will aſſiſt thee particularly in this dangerous paſſage.</p>
            <p n="7">7. By theſe meanes thou
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2106:27"/>shalt receiue great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, &amp; shalt be freed from great apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which perplex many.</p>
            <p n="8">8. After thy death if thou haue any guilt to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, they will aſſiſt thee that thou mayſt be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily deliuered from that clenſing and correcting fier, as S. Auguſtin cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it vpon the ſixt pſalme.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In à word thou shalt recieue à thouſand other
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2106:27"/>bleſſings, which are all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>priſed and farre more in the communion of Saynts; and in that which S. Iames ſaith: <hi>The daily prayer of the iust man is of great force.</hi> Then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, deare brother, if the prayer of one iuſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be of ſoe great valew, how much more merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and auayleable will the continuall prayers of fiue or ſix hundred thouſand ſeruants of god
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2106:28"/>bee; whoe doe dayly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and applye them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to this exerciſe of prayer through the whole world, according to the rule and order of this holy company, to ſollicit thy requeſts &amp; affayres with god; and that eſpecially which is the moſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall of them all, to make à happy end, and to dye in the faith of the church, with the benefit of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, &amp; in the grace of god. Yea euen then
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2106:28"/>when thou doſt walk, ſleepe, eate, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d god, a great number of people fall downe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theire knees, and lift vp theire hands to heauen, beſeeching god to preſerue thee from mortall ſinne, and from a ſinfull death, and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; fearefull iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Therefore, deuout rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, procure this bleſſing for thy ſoule whilſt thou haſt time, and deſpiſe not this fayre occaſion which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2106:29"/>is ſoe eaſy for thee, and without any obligation at all. Think with thy ſelf ſeriouſly what thou wilt wish that thou hadſt done for thy ſelfe, when thou shalt be layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy bed waiting for the laſt ſtroke of death; and pray to god that he will giue thee grace to finde that in thy ſelfe at that hower, &amp; then lett him diſpoſe of thee according to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye will for the reſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="litanies">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2106:29"/>
            <head>THE LETANYES OF OVR LADYE OF LORETTO VVHICH THOSE OF THE COMPANY DOE DAILYE SAYE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>KYrie eleiſon,</item>
               <item>Chriſte eleiſon,</item>
               <item>Kyrie eleiſon,</item>
               <item>Chriſte audi nos,</item>
               <item>Chriſte exaudi nos.</item>
               <item>Pater de coelis Deus, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere nobis.</item>
               <item>Fili redemptor mundi Deus, miſerere nobis.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2106:30"/>
Spiritus ſancte Deus, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere nobis.</item>
               <item>Sancta Trinitas vnus Deus, miſerere nobis.</item>
               <item>Sancta Maria, ora pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</item>
               <item>Sancta Dei genitrix, ora.</item>
               <item>S. Virgo Virginum, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater Chriſti, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater diuinç gratiae, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater puriſsima, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater caſtiſsima, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater inuiolata, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater intemerata, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater amabilis, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater admirabilis, ora.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:2106:30"/>
Mater Creatoris, ora.</item>
               <item>Mater Saluatoris, ora.</item>
               <item>Virgo prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſsima, ora.</item>
               <item>Virgo veneranda, ora.</item>
               <item>Virgo praedicanda, ora.</item>
               <item>Virgo potens, ora.</item>
               <item>Virgo clemens, ora.</item>
               <item>Virgo fidelis, ora.</item>
               <item>Speculum iuſtitiae, ora.</item>
               <item>Sedes ſapientiae, ora.</item>
               <item>Cauſa noſtrae laetitiae, ora.</item>
               <item>Vas ſpirituale, ora.</item>
               <item>Vas honorabile, ora.</item>
               <item>Vas inſigne deuotio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ora.</item>
               <item>Roſa myſtica, ora.</item>
               <item>Turris Dauidica, ora.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:2106:31"/>
Turris eburnea, ora.</item>
               <item>Domus aurea, ora.</item>
               <item>Foederis arca, ora.</item>
               <item>Ianua Coeli, ora.</item>
               <item>Stella matutina, ora.</item>
               <item>Salus infirmorum, ora.</item>
               <item>Refugium peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ora.</item>
               <item>Conſolatio afflictoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina angelorum, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina patriarcharu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina prophetaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina apoſtolorum, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina martyrum, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina confeſſorum, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina virginum, ora.</item>
               <item>Regina Sanctorum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, ora.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2106:31"/>
Mater Dei, ora.</item>
               <item>Agnus Dei, qui tollis pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata mundi, parce nobis Domine.</item>
               <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata mundi, exaudi nos Domine.</item>
               <item>Agnus Dei, qui tollis pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cara mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di, miſerere nobis.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Sub tuum praeſidium confugimus ſancta Dei genitrix noſtras depreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones ne deſpicias in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsiratibus, ſed à periculis cunctis libera nos ſèmpèr Virgo glorioſa &amp; benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2106:32"/>Domina noſtra, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatrix noſtra, tuo filio nos reconcilia, tuo filio nos commenda, tuo filio nos in hora mortis praeſenta: ſancta Maria ſuccurre mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeris, iuua puſillanimes, re. foue flebiles, ora pro po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo, interueni pro clero, intercede pro deuoto foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineo ſenu; ſentiant om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes tuum juuamen, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumque celebrant tuam ſanctam commemoraetio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers:</hi> Ora pro nobis pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoribus
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2106:32"/>ſancta Mariae mater Dei.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp:</hi> Nunc &amp; in hora mortis noſtrae.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſancte Ioſeph.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Nunc &amp; in hora mortis noſtrae.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſancte Auguſtine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Nunc &amp; in hora mortis noſtrae.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers:</hi> Ora pro nobis beate Franciſce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Nunc &amp; in hora mortis noſtrae.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2106:33"/>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſancta Barbara.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Nunc &amp; in hora mortis noſtrae.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Memento Domine Congregationis tuę.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Quam poſſediſti ab initio.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> A ſubitanea &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouiſa morte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Libera nos Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Ab inſidijs Diaboli.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Libera nos Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> A poenis inferni.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:2106:33"/>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Libera nos Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Saluos fac ſeruos tuos.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Deus meus ſperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in te.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Domine exaudi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem meam.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Et clamor meus ad te veniat.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Oremus.</head>
            <p>GRatiam tuam quaeſumus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. mentibus noſtris in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funde, vt qui angelo nunciante Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> filij tui incarnationem cognouimus, per paſsionem eius
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2106:34"/>&amp; crucem, ad reſurrectionis glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam perducamur.</p>
            <p>Defende quaeſumus Domine beata Maria ſemper Virgine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedente, iſtam ab omni adner, ſitate familiam, &amp; toto corde titi proſtraram ab hoſtium pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ius tuere clementer inſidijs.</p>
            <p>Sanctiſsimae genitricis tuae ſponſi quaeſumus Domine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis adiuuemur, vt quod poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas noſtra non obtinet eius nobis interceſsione donetur.</p>
            <p>Adeſto ſupplicationibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is omnipotens Deus, &amp; quibus fiduciam ſperandae pietatis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulges intercedente beato Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtino confeſſore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uo, atque pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice conſuetae miſericordiae tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bue benignus effectum.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2106:34"/>
Deus qui Eccleſiam tuam beati Franciſci meritis foetu nouę pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis amphficas: tribue nobis ex eius imitatione terrena deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, &amp; coeleſtium donor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>um ſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per participatione gaudere.</p>
            <p>Interceſsio quaeſumus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine beatae Barbarae Virginis, &amp; Martyris tuae ab omni aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate nos protegat, vt per eius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ruen tum glorioſum, ſacroſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum coiporis Domini noſtri ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum, ante diem exitus noſtri per veram poenitentiam, &amp; puram confeſsionem percipere mereamur.</p>
            <p>Da nobis quaeſumus Domine perſeuetantem in voluntate tua famulatum, vi in diebus noſtris. &amp; merito, &amp; numero populus
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2106:35"/>tibi ſeruiens augeatur.</p>
            <p>Praetende Domine famulis, &amp; famulabus tuis dextera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coeleſtis auxilij, vt te toto corde perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant &amp; quae digne poſtulant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequi mereantur.</p>
            <p>Actiones noſtras quaeſumus Domine aſpirando praeueni, &amp; adiuuando proſequere, vt cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cta noſtra oratio, &amp; operatio, atque bene viuendi inſticutio, à te ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per incipiat, &amp; per te coepta fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niatur: Qui in trinitate perfecta viuis &amp; regnas Deus, in ſecula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2106:35"/>
            <head>PRAYERS FOR THE SOVLES OF THOSE WHOE ARE DEPARTED OF THE HOLY COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PANY.</head>
            <p>DE profundis cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maui ad te Domine: Domine exaudi vocem meam.</p>
            <p>Fiant aures tuae inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes: in vocem depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis meae.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2106:36"/>
Si iniquitates obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueris Domine: Domine quis ſuſtinebit?</p>
            <p>Quia apud te propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatio eſt: &amp; propter lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuam ſuſtinui te Domine.</p>
            <p>Suſtinuit anima mea in verbo eius: ſperauit ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mea in Domino.</p>
            <p>A cuſtodia matutina vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad noctem: ſperet Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raël in Domino.</p>
            <p>Quia apud Dominum miſericordia: &amp; copioſa apud eum redemptio.</p>
            <p>Et ipſe redimet Iſrael:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2106:36"/>ex omnibus iniquitatibus eius.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers:</hi> Requiem aeternam dona eis Domine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Et lux perpetua lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat eis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> A porta inferi.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp:</hi> Erue Domine ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas eorum.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers:</hi> Requieſcant in pace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp:</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers:</hi> Domine exaudi o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem meam.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Et. clamor meus ad te veniat.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:2106:37"/>
            <head>Oremus.</head>
            <p>DEus veniae largitor, &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae ſalutis amator, quaeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt noſtrae aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciationis fideles, qui ex hocſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo tranſierunt, beata Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ia ſemper virgine intercedente, cum omnibus ſanctis tuis ad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuae beatitudinis conſortium peruenire concedas: Per Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Dominum noſtrum. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn">
            <head>ANTHEME OF THE HOLY VIRGIN AND MARTYR S. BARBARA.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Gaude beata Barbara,</l>
               <l>Summa pollens doctrina,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2106:37"/>
Angeli myſterio.</l>
               <l>Gaude virgo Deo grata,</l>
               <l>Quae Baptiſtam es imitata,</l>
               <l>In vitae ſtadio.</l>
               <l>Gaude cum te viſitauit,</l>
               <l>Chriſtus vita, &amp; curauit</l>
               <l>Plagas actu proptio.</l>
               <l>Gaude quia meruiſti,</l>
               <l>Impetrare quod petiſti,</l>
               <l>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te Dei filio.</l>
               <l>Gaude, namque es eleuata,</l>
               <l>Et in coelum es delata,</l>
               <l>Nobili mattyrio.</l>
               <l>Te laudantem familiam,</l>
               <l>Trahe poſt te ad gloriam,</l>
               <l>Finito exilio.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Vers.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſanctiſsima Virgo Barbara.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Vt digni efficiamur pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionibus Chriſti.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:2106:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2106:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:2106:39"/>
            <head>Oremus.</head>
            <p>INterceſſio quaeſumus Domine beatae Barbarę Virginis, &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyris tuae ab omni aduerſitate nos protegat, vt per eius interuentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glorioſum ſacro-ſanctum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti ſacramentum ante diem exitus noſtri per veram pęnitentiam &amp; puram confeſſionem; atque etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> extremam vnctionem percipere mereamur: per eundem Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Dominum noſtrum Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:2106:39"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT TOVCHING THE FORESAYD ANTHEME AND PRAYER.</head>
            <p>YOu shall knovv that amongſt the holy patrons of this bleſſed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitye S. Barbara is rightly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, forasmuch as shee hath that guift and grace from god to preſerue from ſoddayne, and vnprouided death all ſuch as doe demand it of god in her name. As it doth appeare in the acts of her noble martyrdome vvhich you shall ſind in the lines of Saynts vvitten by the reuerend fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rybadeneyra: vvith a notable
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2106:40"/>example of one, vvho falling dovv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from the topp of a houſe that vvas on fire, and being buried, or rather ouervvhelmed vvith the ruynes of the houſe, and flaming brands, vvas in due time ſuccored by the ſayd Saynt, vvhoe appeared vnto him and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him that he should not dye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had receiued the Sacraments; and for that end thee had obtayned of god a reſpit for him till the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t day: vvhich ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fell out, and he made a most happy end; becauſe for a great ſpace of tyme he had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the foreſayd Saynt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:2106:40"/>
            <head>A PRAYER TO IESVS CHRIST CRVCIFIED.</head>
            <p>O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, my moſt mercifull ſauiour, I beſeech thee by that great bitternes, which thou didſt ſuffer on the croſſe for me wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner; eſpecially at that houre when thy moſt ſanctified ſoule did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thy bleſſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, that it would pleaſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2106:41"/>thee to haue pitty on my ſoule, and to vſe mercye thereto when it shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this life, and that thou wouldeſt by the merits of thy moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud take it with thee into aeternall life. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>Caeſarius a religious man doth report, that a great ſeruant of god being accouſtomed to ſay the forſayd prayer as often as he paſſed by the holy Crucifix, did merit after
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2106:41"/>his death to goe out of this vvorld directly into paradiſe, vvithout ſuffring the paynes of purgatory.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of_contrition">
            <head>AN ACT OF CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRITION, WITH ALL THE PARTS THEREOF IN FORME OF A PRAYER.</head>
            <p>MY lord Ieſus Chriſt, true god, &amp; true ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for aſmuch as thou art ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished with all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and becauſe I doe acknowledg thee for my ſouueraigne bilſſe, I do
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2106:42"/>loue thee with all my hart and aboue all things I am infinitly ſory that I haue ſoe vngratefully offended thee. Wherefore I doe firſt of all reſolue neuer to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee more. Secondly to flye from all the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſinne. Thirdly to make a ſincere confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to performe ſuch pennance, as shall be enioyned to mee: and for a more full, &amp; worthy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I doe offer vnto thee thy owne merits,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2106:42"/>with thoſe of the bleſſed virgin thy mother, and of all thoſe whom thou haſt elected, ioyning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with both my body and foule, my temptations, ſorrowes, and afflictions, and my whole life. Beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee alſoe that thou wouldſt pardonne, and giue me thy grace, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may amend my life; and that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> till my death. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:2106:43"/>
            <head>A PRAYER TO OVR BLESSED LADY TO COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEND OVR SELVES TO HER SPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIALL PROTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTION AND SAFEGARD.</head>
            <p>O Domina mea ſancta Maria ego infaelix peccator me in tuam be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictam fidem ac ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larem cuſtodiam, &amp; in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num miſericordiae tuae ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diè &amp; quotidiè, &amp; in hora
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2106:43"/>exitus mei, animam mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; corpus meum tibi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo; omnem ſpem meam, &amp; conſolationem meam, omnes anguſtias, &amp; miſerias meas, vitam, &amp; finem vitae meae tibi comitto; te hodie matre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; apud Deum aduocata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prae omnibus eligo, &amp; pręopto; tu quę pijſſima es mater miſericordiae, noli me propter nimia peccata mea reijcere: ſed pertuam ſanctiſſimam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſionem, &amp; per tua
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2106:44"/>glorioſa merita, omnia mea dirigantur &amp; diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur opera, ſecundum tuam, tui<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> filij volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>AN OTHER PRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>YER TO IMPLORE THE AYDE OF OVR BLESSED LADY IN TIME OF TRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BVLATION, AND IN HORROR OF DEATH.</head>
            <p>O Moſt chaſt, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull virgin, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2106:44"/>mother holy Mary, ſtretch forth I beſeech thee, the hand of thy help and ſuccor to me a miſerable and wretched ſinner in all thoſe trauayles, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsityes which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto me at any time or place; but principally in this tribulation and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction which doth op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe me at this preſent, ſoe that I may not onely beare it patiently, and for the loue of god, but alſoe with courage, and chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refully
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2106:45"/>and that by his grace and ſpeciall aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance I may gayne force and conſtancy in all my other croſſes and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſityes, which may fall vpon me, aſwell from the hand of my god, as of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O mother of mercy and aduocate of ſinners be pleaſed alſoe to be my gratious defendreſſe at that time when my ſoule shall part from my body; for at that time more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other shall I haue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2106:45"/>neede of thy ſuccor and ayde. For alas if I conſider the weight of my ſinnes, and the number of offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces which I haue committed and doe daily committ in the preſence of the diuine goodnes, I feare to be confounded &amp; ouercome by the deuill, whoe will neuer ceaſe to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before my eyes indeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to deceiue me by his falſe illuſions. I therfore moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeech thee, the true diſtributor of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2106:46"/>gods holy graces) that thou wouldeſt obtayne of my lord, thy deare and onely ſonne, true god, and true man, that as he hath vouchſafed to come and take humayne flesh in thy chaſt wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, not by any humayne but Diuine power, that ſo he might ſaue mankind from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation; ſoe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would pleaſe him to giue me the force and vnderſtanding at that laſt houre truely to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2106:46"/>of my ſinnes, and to haue nothing in my thoughts but him alone. Which I aske by thy inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion not for my ſelf alone, but alſoe for all thoſe whoe are of this holy ſocietye whereof thou art the principall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye &amp; miſtreſſe ſoe that by thy merits &amp; interceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee may all ſoe well ſerue thy moſt ſweete ſonne in our life, that acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him at our death by recieuing al the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2106:47"/>and his holye grace, wee may merit one daye in heauen to enioy and poſſeſſe without end, the cleare viſion of the bleſſed. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>AN OTHER PRAYER TO OVR LADYE.</head>
            <p>O Moſt mercifull vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marye, moſt worthy mother of god, aſſured refuge of ſinners, conforter of the afflicted, I vnworthy ſinner haue
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2106:47"/>recourſe to thee with great confidence, beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee for that great ioye, which thou didſt feele in thy hart, when thou didſt ſee thy onely deare ſonne riſe from death to life, that it would pleaſe thee to comfort my ſoule: and more expreſſely I beſeech the for a ſpeciall grace, by the bowells of thy infinite pittye, that in the laſt paſſage of my life whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I shall appeare trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling defore the awefull
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2106:48"/>tribunall of thy deare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſonne my ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to giue a ſtrict accompt of my whole life, that thou wouldeſt vouchſafe to aſsiſt and prorect me, to the end that by thy fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable interceſsion (moſt gracious mother) I may eſcape that terrible ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of eternall death, &amp; be found, or made worthy to enioy with thee that life which neuer shall haue end. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2106:48"/>
            <head>PROTESTATIONS FOR THOSE WHOE ARE SICK AND DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIRE TO DYE IN THE GRACE OF GOD.</head>
            <p n="1">I. N. miferable ſinner doe proteſt heere in the preſence of the holy Trinity, the Father, So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, and Holy ghoſt, of Ieſus Chriſt crucified for my ſinnes, of the glorious virgin Marye our aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, of S. Michael the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changell,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2106:49"/>and of all the angells, and ſaynts in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, eſpecially my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell gardien and of my patrone S. N. and other Saynts my aduocats and interceſſors, and of all yee my parents and friends that are here preſent, whom I deſire to be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of what I shall ſpeake. I doe then firſt of all proteſt that I doe take in good part my death, &amp; with all willingnes of mind; and that I doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2106:49"/>ſuffer the griefes and afflictions of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe for the loue, &amp; glory of the diuine maieſtye; yea euen the paynes of purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye for ſuch time as it shall pleaſe our lord for the remiſſion of my ſinnes &amp; the punishment due vnto them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I proteſt that I will dye as I haue liued in the true faith of the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, Apoſtolique, and Romayne church; and, I doe beleeue and hold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolably
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2106:50"/>whatſoeuer it doth beleeue, and propoſe vnto me to be beleeued, with all the articles of the Creed which I will now repeate; <hi>Credo in Deum</hi> &amp;c: and therewithall I doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue condemne, and deteſt all the ancient and moderne hereſyes, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally that of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts and Proteſtants of our times.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I doe proteſt that I doe entirely truſt in the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite bounty and mercy of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2106:50"/>my god and ſauiour, the which doth infinitely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede all my ſinnes, how great or grieuous ſoeuer they be. And therefore I doe hope to be ſaued, not by my merits, but by the merits of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious bloud, of the paſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and death of Ieſus Chriſt, the onely true ſauiour of my ſoule.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I proteſt that I doe pardon with all my hart all thoſe, whoe haue at any time offended me wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2106:51"/>them all happynes &amp; proſperitye in our Lord beſeeching their pardon for euery occaſion or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect that I may haue giuen them to offend me.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I doe proteſt that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bottome of my hart, and with all profound humility I doe ask pardon of all thoſe whome I may at any time haue ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſed by my ill example, or in any other ſort what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer offended in word, or deed eyther in body,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2106:51"/>goods, or fame; offring my ſelf with all readynes to giue them all manner of ſatisfaction, as farre, as I shall be able.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I doe proteſt, being humbly proſtrated before the diume maieſty, that from the bottome of my hart I doe ask pardon and for giuenes for all my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and offences which I haue committed agaynſt him, agaynſt my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp; my ſelf: being chiefely greeued, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2106:52"/>troubled in my ſoule that I haue tranſgreſſed his will, conſidering his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodnes and merit, and in regard of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and notorious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors, which it hath pleaſed him to beſtowe vpon me; much offended with my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that I haue not had that griefe, ſorowe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition, which I ought, and should deſire to haue, and that I haue not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture confeſſed my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as I ought, and am o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2106:52"/>to doe; for which I am hartyly ſorye, and doe propoſe to my ſelf for the time to come in better manner then I haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto done, to ſerue god faithfully, for euer remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my ſelf to his diuine prouidence, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall goodnes.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I doe proteſt that I giue thankes with the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt power and forces of my hart to my lord my god, for all the benefits already recieued, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2106:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:2106:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:2106:54"/>which I doe hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieue from his diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye, which are infinite. I doe alſoe thank all thoſe whoe in any manner whatſoeuer haue eyther done, or deſired any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, ſeruice, or good office, eyther for my ſoule or bodye; and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely and particularly thoſe whoe haue eyther giuen or offered me any occaſion to merit.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I proteſt that I doe offer to my lord and god
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2106:54"/>all the ſatisfactions, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſorrowes, with the bloud which hath bene shed by my ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the bleſſed virgin Mary, of all the Saynts, &amp; ſeruants of god, whoe shall liue heere till the end of the world, for the remiſsion and ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all my ſinnes, and for a perpetuall tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgiuing, and fit acknowledgment of the infinite benefits, &amp; graces recieued of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2106:55"/>maieſtye.</p>
            <p n="9">9. I proteſt that I doe moſt humbly beſeech the ſacred virgin Marye, my angell gardie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, my patron, and the ſaynts to whom I haue ſpeciall deuotion, with all the angells, and Saynts of paradiſe that they would ayd and aſſiſt me at my laſt poynt of life and obtayne for me by theire interceſſions, and merits euerlaſting repoſe in their bleſſed company. Marye mother of grace
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2106:55"/>mother of mercie protect vs from our ennemye, &amp; recieue vs at the houre of death. All the ſaynts of heauen make interceſſion for me.</p>
            <p n="10">10. I proteſt that if ſoe be that our Lord permit that I should be tempted by the deuill with any temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation whatſoeuer eyther agaynſt faith, hope, or charity towards god, or neighbour, or agaynſt ought that I haue nowe ſayd, that I will not
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2106:56"/>harken, anſweare, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent thereto, or beleeue his falſe perſwaſions, and if ſoe be that by his craft and deceipts, or by the violence of my maladie and payne I should happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to conſent to any ſinne, I doe nowe beſeech my good god that ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of mine may be voyd &amp; of none effect; and this I ask for the valewe and merit of the precious bloud of my Lord &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:2106:56"/>
Finally I proteſt that I doe recommend at this preſent my poore ſoule to the ſacred wounds of the feete, hands, and ſide of my ſweete and mercyfull ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, the which I doe kiſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace with all my hart, in the which I will liue and dye. Betwixt the armes of my redeemer I will liue, and I deſire to dye: Into thy hands ô lord I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend my ſpirit: Thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me my lord god
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2106:57"/>of truth, god of my hart, and my portion for euer. I beſeech all thoſe whoe are preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at my houre of death, &amp; when I shal not be able to ſpeak any more that they would ayd, &amp; ſuccor me with their prayers offring vp to the eternall father my ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, ſweate, &amp; ſuffrings in the vnion of the agonye, ſweates, and ſuffrings, of the bloud, paynes, and paſſions of my well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Ieſus Chriſt for the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2106:57"/>remiſsion of my ſinnes.</p>
            <p>When thou shalt haue ended theſe proteſtations, the which thou mayſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite many times, if thou think good, thou shalt ſay with great reuerence, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and attention the two prayers; the one to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt Crucified, the other to the B. Virgin; by which is demanded grace to make a happy paſſage from this life to the next: which prayers are placed aboue pag. 65 and pag. 78.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="directions">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:2106:58"/>
            <head>OTHER DIRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTIONS VERY PIOVS AND PROFITABLE.</head>
            <p n="1">1. After the foreſayd proteſtations and prayers it is requiſite that the aſſiſtants with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible voyce should ſaye the letanyes of our ladye, or thoſe of the ſaynts, and that the ſick party should indeuor to anſweare at leaſt by hart,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2106:58"/>if hee cannot by mouth, to the end that hee may more ſurely obtayne the grace which is deſired. Then shall he kiſſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred wounds of the holy Crucifix, ſayeing each time, <hi>Ieſu the ſonne of Dauid haue mercy vpon me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſick perſon shall cauſe a Crucifix, or ſome other deuout image of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, or our bleſſed Lady to be hung vp in ſome place where he may eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:2106:59"/>hold, and contemplate it many times, as well by nyght as by day, and pray ſometimes to Ieſus Chriſt, ſometimes to our bleſſed ladye, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding himſelf cordially vnto them to ſpeake theſe words, or ſuch like. O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus my ſauuiour ſaue my ſoule. O mercifull virgin Marye defend my ſoule. O Ieſus and Marye grant patience and ſtrength to my ſoule. O Ieſus and Marie recieue my ſoule
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2106:59"/>neere vnto yee. He shall likewiſe reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the bleſſed patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs S. Ioſeph, Saint Francis, Saint Auguſtin, and Saynt Barbara, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall protectors and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors for the holy Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of twelue, and to other his particular fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, and deuout perſons, and aboue all to his good Angell guardien.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theye whoe haue charge of the ſick partyes shall be carefull that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2106:60"/>theire children, or ſuch like perſons, doe not come neere them, or but very ſeldome by reaſon of the particular and naturall affection that they beare to them, becauſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſuch perſons doth vſually trouble ſicke people, for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derneſſe of affection which is ſtirred vp in them, which is very hurtfull as well to the body as to the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All laſciuious pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, &amp; profane pictures,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2106:60"/>are to be remoued from the chamber of the ſick body, or at leaſt to be kept out of his ſight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they might without doubt cauſe in him, by the craft of the deuill euill thoughts, and effects.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thoſe whoe shall viſit the ſick, muſt be carefull that they doe not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne them with vayne diſcourſe, or vnproffitable and worldly buiſineſſes: but shall ſpeake vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch things as may ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2106:61"/>recreate them, and edify the aſsiſtants in our Lord.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſick partye shall be diligent to diſcouer vnto his ſpirituall father all the temptations, doubts, ſcruples, and ſinnes, orderly as they come to his memorye, to the end, that conſeruing by this meane the peace and tranquillity of his conſcience, the deuill be not able to deceiue him in any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:2106:61"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Beſides the ſick, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe whoe attend about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, muſt indeuor to gett <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eligious men to come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ften vnto him, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arly his confeſſor or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ituall father, that he may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ayded by them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orted, &amp; ſolaced, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly towards the end of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is life. For it is certayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>that the preſence onely of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood religious men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ially if they be prieſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth bring, &amp; cauſe great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are and terror to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2106:62"/>deuills, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forſake the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon till he be dead.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To conclude, I will ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one thing very profitable for ſick perſons, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make a good, and quiet end; and which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance is not much pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by worldly men which is; not to put of the ſayeing of maſſes for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after theire death, or t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> giue almes for the goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theire ſoules; but they ought to doe it whill
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2106:62"/>they liue, for as much as ſuch like good workes, are then without compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon farre more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the ſoule then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theire death. Firſt for that they obtayne of god diuerſity of proffit, and ſpirituall helpes, with, or by which the ſoule is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to doe ſupernaturall workes, and which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue eternall ſaluation, as acts of forrowe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition for ſinne, of the loue of god, hope, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2106:63"/>ſuch like, by which a habit of diuine grace doth increaſe in the ſoule, and conſequently the glory which is due thereto in paradiſe. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſoule doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of theſe ſpirituall helps, great force, and is meruailouſly ſtrengthned and incouraged in time of death agaynſt the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of his ennemy. In a word theſe meanes are of great force and vale we to obtayne of god a true and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2106:63"/>harty repentance at the houre of death, and a moſt perfect conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him; wherein a happye end doth conſiſt, and in his grace, and conſequently our eternall ſaluation in the life to come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto may it pleaſe our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer to conduct vs all by the merits of his moſt holy paſſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:2106:64"/>
            <head>THE COMPLAINT OF A SOVLE APPRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HENDING THE AETERNITYE OF HELL.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>FOr EVER,</hi> neuer ending, my good god,</l>
               <l>S'an infinite that knovvs no period:</l>
               <l>Reſtleſſe, hovvlinge, burninge, dyinge <hi>EVER,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So endleſſe each a part, and all togeather.</l>
               <l>If after many thouſand yeares
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2106:64"/>vvere past,</l>
               <l>Theſe ills should end, there vvould be hope at last.</l>
               <l>But this for <hi>EVER</hi> termeleſſe all conſumes,</l>
               <l>And old past Age, its infancy reſumes.</l>
               <l>The fulleſt mirth hard <hi>EVER</hi> doth controule,</l>
               <l>And ſad, and ſilent strikes th'afflicted ſoule.</l>
               <l>By Attoms could a vvrenne ouer the mayne,</l>
               <l>Transfer the headleſſe Alpes, vvith easleſſe payne;</l>
               <l>And euery thouſand yeares
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2106:65"/>but once could fly:</l>
               <l>Or vvhen an Ant had ſuckt the Ocean dry,</l>
               <l>Should be the terme; this tardy hope might pleaſe,</l>
               <l>The Damned ſoules; that once there vvould be eaſe.</l>
               <l>But Horred <hi>EVER,</hi> tyme, and all or'e paſt:</l>
               <l>Exiſts alone, vvith him that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt, and laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="office">
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:65"/>
            <head>OFFICIVM PARVVM in honorem S. IOSEPH Sponſi B. Mariae.</head>
            <div type="canonical_hour">
               <head>AD MATVTINVM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ieſus, Maria, Ioſeph.</p>
               <p>DOmine labia mea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:2106:66"/>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Et os meum annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciabit laudem ruam.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Deus in adiutorium meum intende.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Domine ad adiuuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum me feſtina.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Gloria Patri, &amp; Filio: &amp; Spiritui ſancto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Sicut erat in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, &amp; nunc, &amp; ſemper: &amp; in ſecula ſeculorum, Amen. Alleluia.</p>
               <p>A <hi>ſeptuageſima vſque ad Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha, loco</hi> Alleluia, <hi>dicitur,</hi> Laus tibi Domine, Rex aeternae gloriae. <hi>Hymnus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:2106:66"/>
IOſeph Dauid filius clara ſtirpe natus,</p>
               <p>Virgini dèſponſus, mente copulatus,</p>
               <p>Vtriuſque cuſtos, caelo de (ſtinatus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiphona.</hi> Salue Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triar charum decus, &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ſanctę Dei oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, cui panem vitae, &amp; frumentum electorum conſeruaſti.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte Ioſeph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Vrdigni efficiamur promiſſionibus Chriſti.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:2106:67"/>
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>SAnctiſsimae Genitricis tuae ſponſi, quęſumus Domine, meritis adiuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur: vt quod poſsibilitas noſtra non obtinet, eius nobis interceſsione done<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Qui viuis, &amp; regnas cum Deo Patre in vnitate Spiritus ſancti Deus, per omnia ſecula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="canonical_hour">
               <head>AD PRIMAN.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ieſus, Maria, Ioſeph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſus.</hi> DEus in adiutorium meum intende. <hi>Reſp.</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:2106:67"/>
Domine ad adiuuandum me feſtina. <hi>Verſ.</hi> Gloria Patri, &amp; Filio: &amp; Spiritui ſancto. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Sicut erat in principio, &amp; nunc &amp; ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: &amp; in ſecula ſeculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Amen. Alleluia.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>Hymnus.</head>
                  <p>TV, qui ſponſam gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidam dolens cùm videres,</p>
                  <p>Cogitabas anxius an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am retineres,</p>
                  <p>Sed coeleſtis nuntius, ne ampliùs tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res,</p>
                  <p>In ſomnis admonuit,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:2106:68"/>ſed potiùs gauderes. <hi>Antiphona.</hi> Salue Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charum decus, &amp; Eccleſię ſanctę Dei oeconomus, cui panem vitae, &amp; frumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> electorum conſeruaſti. <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſancte Ioſeph. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Vt digni effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamur promiſsionibus Chriſti.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>SAnctiſsimae Genitricis tuae ſponſi, quaeſumus Domine, meritis adiuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur: vt quod poſsibilitas noſtra non obtinet, eius
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2106:68"/>nobis interceſsione done<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Qui viuis, &amp; regnas cum Deo Patre in vnitate Spiritus ſancti Deus: per omnia ſecula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="canonical_hour">
               <head>AD TERTIAM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ieſus, Maria, Ioſeph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſus.</hi> DEus in adiutorium meum intende. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Domine ad adiuuandum me feſtina. <hi>Verſ.</hi> Gloria Patri &amp; Filio: &amp; Spiritui ſancto. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Sicut erat in principio, &amp; nunc, &amp;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2106:69"/>ſemper: &amp; in ſecula ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum. Amen. Alleluia.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>Hymnus.</head>
                  <p>BEthleem profectus cenſum ſoluturus,</p>
                  <p>Cum praegnante Virgine, vbi naſciturus</p>
                  <p>Erat mundi Dominus, quippe mox facturus,</p>
                  <p>Vtipſum infantulum eſſet ample xurus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antiph.</hi> Salue Patriarcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum decus, &amp; Eccleſiae ſanctae Dei oeconomus, cui panem vitae, &amp; fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum electorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruaſti.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2106:69"/>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſancte Ioſeph.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Vt digni efficiamur promiſsionibus Chriſti.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>SAnctiſsimae Genitricis tuae ſponſi, quaeſumus Domine, meritis adiuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur; Vt quod poſsibilitas, noſtra non obtinet, eius nobis interceſsione done<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Qui viuis, &amp; regnas cum Deo Patre, in vnitate Spiritus ſancti Deus: per omnia ſecula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="canonical_hour">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:2106:70"/>
               <head>AD SEXTAM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ieſus, Maria, Ioſeph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſus.</hi> DEus in adiutorium meum intende.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Domine ad adiuuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum me feſtina.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Gloria Patri, &amp; Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>Hymnus.</head>
                  <p>CVm Herodes impius in pueros ſaeuiret,</p>
                  <p>Gabrielis monitu ne am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliùs dormiret,</p>
                  <p>Retuliſti ſponſae, ſed te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum veniret,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:2106:70"/>
Et accepto paruulo in AEgyptum iret.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antiph.</hi> Salue Patriarcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum decus, &amp; Eccleſiae ſanctae Dei oeconomus, cui panem vitae, &amp; fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum electorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruaſti.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſancte Ioſeph.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Vt digni efficiamur promiſsionibus Chriſti.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>SAnctiſsimae Genitricis tuae ſponſi, quaeſumus Domine, meritis adiuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur:
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2106:71"/>vt quod poſsibilitas noſtra non obtinet, eius nobis interceſſione done<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Qui viuis, &amp; regnas cum Deo Patre in vnitate Spiritus ſancti Deus, per omnia ſecula ſeculorum, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="canonical_hour">
               <head>AD NONAM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ieſus Maria, Ioſeph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſus.</hi> DEus in adiutorium meum intende.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Domine ad adiuuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum me feſtina.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Gloria Patri &amp; Filio:
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2106:71"/>&amp; Spiritui ſancto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Sicut erat in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, &amp; nunc, &amp; ſemper: &amp; in ſecula ſeculorum. Amen. Alleluia.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>Hymnus.</head>
                  <p>HOſtibus defunctis inde receſsiſti,</p>
                  <p>Et in Galilaeam tecum reduxiſti,</p>
                  <p>Puerum, &amp; ſponſam, ſicut didiciſti</p>
                  <p>Cęlitus, &amp; Nazareth humilis vixiſti. <hi>Antiph.</hi> Salue Patriarcharum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp; Eccleſiae ſanctae Dei oeconomus, cui pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:2106:72"/>vitę &amp; frumentum ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum conſeruaſti.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ora pro nobis ſancte Ioſeph. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Vt digni effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamur promiſsionibus Chriſti.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>SAnctiſsimae Genitricis tuae ſponſi, quaeſumus Domine, meritis adiuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur: vt quod poſſibilitas noſtra non obtinet, eius nobis interceſsione done<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Qui viuis, &amp; regnas cum Deo patre in vnitate Spiritus ſancti Deus, per
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2106:72"/>omnia ſecula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="canonical_hour">
               <head>AD VESPERAS.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ieſus, Maria, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph..</p>
               <p>DEus in adiutorium meum intende. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Domine ad adiuuandum me feſtina.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Sicut erat &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>Hymnus.</head>
                  <p>O Qui Ieſum factum duo decim annorum Perdidiſti tuum lumen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorum!</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:2106:73"/>
Sed inuentum poſtea in medio doctorum,</p>
                  <p>Cuſtodiſti ſedulus, Regem Angelorum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antiph.</hi> Salue patriarcharu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> decus, &amp; Eccleſiae ſanctae Dei oeconomus, cui pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitae, &amp; frumentum ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum conſeruaſti. <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ora pro nobis &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>SAnctiſsimae Genitricis tuae ſponſi quaeſumus Domine, meritis adiuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur: vt quod poſsibilitas noſtra non obtinet eius
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2106:73"/>nobis interceſsione do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur. Qui viuis, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="canonical_hour">
               <head>AD COMPLETORIVM.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Ieſus, Maria, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph..</p>
               <p>COnuerte nos Deus ſalutaris noſter. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Et auerre iram tuam à no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Deus in adiutorium meum intende.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Domine ad adiuuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum me feſtina.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>Hymnus.</head>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:2106:74"/>
                  <p>Faelix, quem in vlnis Ieſus cum Maria</p>
                  <p>Tenuit cubantem, dum in agonia</p>
                  <p>Spiritum efflares, vt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recta via,</p>
                  <p>Tenderes ad Patres fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus vita pia,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antiph.</hi> Salue Patriarcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum decus, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>SAnctiſsimae Genitricis tuae ſponſi, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commendation">
               <head>Commendatio.</head>
               <p>HAs horas Canonicas cum attentione.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:2106:74"/>
Dixi ſancte Ioſeph tui ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</p>
               <p>Vt ſis memor mei in ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</p>
               <p>Vt viuamus ſimul in coeli regione. Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:75"/>
            <p>Hic libellus, eui titulus ASSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIATIONIS, ſiue SOCIETATIS; VNA CVM OFFICIO S. IOSEPH, tranſlatus ex Gallico in Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Anglicum, vriliter excude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Actum Duaci 20. Maij. 1626.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEORGIVS COLVENERIVS, S. Th. Doctor, &amp; Regius ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariuſque Profeſſor, &amp; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demia Duacena Libroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cenſor</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2106:75"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
